Mira Lloyd Dock Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Mira Lloyd Dock Papers 1814-1951 (bulk 1899-1945)
MSS18689
Dock, Mira Lloyd, 1853-1945
2,500 items
11 containers plus 1 oversize
4.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Horticulturalist, conservationist, educator, and clubwoman. Correspondence, printed matter, speeches and writings, clippings, photographs, maps, and other papers relating primarily to Dock's efforts in forestry, conservation, gardening, park development, and nature study in Pennsylvania and elsewhere in the United States as well as in Germany and England.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bartram, John G. (John Greer), 1893-1955.; Bascom, F. (Florence), 1862-1945--Correspondence.; Brandis, Dietrich, Sir, 1824-1907--Correspondence.; Crocker, Marion A., 1867-1957--Correspondence.; Dock family--Correspondence.; Dock family--Genealogy.; Dock, Mira Lloyd, 1853-1945.; Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920--Correspondence.; Jäger, T. B.--Correspondence.; Lloyd family--Correspondence.; Lloyd family--Genealogy.; Manning, Warren H. (Warren Henry), 1860- --Correspondence.; McFarland, J. Horace (John Horace), 1859-1948--Correspondence.; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946--Correspondence.; Rothrock, Joseph T., 1839-1922--Correspondence.; Sargent, Charles Sprague, 1841-1927--Correspondence.; Sherman, Mary Belle King, 1865-1935--Correspondence.; Surface, H. A. (Harvey Adam), 1867-1941--Correspondence.
Organizations
General Federation of Women's Clubs.; Lorberry Creek Railroad.; Pennsylvania. State Forestry Reservation Commission.; State Federation of Pennsylvania Women.
Subjects
Arbor Day.; Civic improvement.; Conservation of natural resources--England.; Conservation of natural resources--Germany.; Conservation of natural resources--Pennsylvania.; Conservation of natural resources--United States.; Conservation of natural resources.; Forest fires.; Forestry schools and education--England.; Forestry schools and education--Germany.; Forestry schools and education--Pennsylvania.; Forestry schools and education--United States.; Forestry schools and education.; Forests and forestry--England.; Forests and forestry--Germany.; Forests and forestry--Pennsylvania.; Forests and forestry--United States.; Forests and forestry.; Gardening.; Horticulture--England.; Horticulture--Germany.; Horticulture--Pennsylvania.; Horticulture--United States.; Horticulture.; Parks--Design and construction.; Playgrounds.; Railroads--Pennsylvania.; Trees.; Urban beautification.; Women--Societies and clubs.
Places
Black Forest (Germany)--Description and travel.; England--Description and travel.; Europe--Description and travel.
Occupations
Clubwomen.; Conservationists.; Educators.; Horticulturists.
Provenance
The papers of Mira Lloyd Dock, horticulturist, conservationist, educator, and clubwoman, were given to the Library of Congress by her estate through her sister Lavinia L. Dock from 1945 to 1948.
Transfers
Some broadsides have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of the Dock Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Mira Lloyd Dock are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1853, Dec. 25 Born, Harrisburg, Pa.
1895 1896 Studied plant biology, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Mich.
1897 Chairman, Program Committee, Pennsylvania Federation of Women's Clubs
1898 circa 1932 Cofounder and member, Civic Club, Harrisburg, Pa.
1899 Invited by the Metropolitian Public Gardens Association of London, England, to present paper to the horticultural section, International Congress of Women, London, England Representated the State Federation of Pennsylvania Women and City Parks Association of Philadelphia, Pa., at the International Congress of Women, London, England Studied forestry and urban arboriculture in England and Germany under auspices of the Pennsylvania Department of Agriculture
1901 1913 First female member, State Forestry Reservation Commission of Pennsylvania
1903 1929 Teacher, Pennsylvania State Forest Academy, Mont Alto, Pa.
1904 1913 Chairman of forestry, State Federation of Pennsylvania Women
1910 Vice-chairman, Conservation Committee, General Federation of Women's Clubs
1911 Member, Advisory Committee, Pennsylvania State Branch of the National Conservation Association
1912 Member, Board of Directors, Pennsylvania School of Horticulture for Women, Ambler, Pa.
1914 circa 1924 Chairman, Forestry Committee, General Federation of Women's Clubs
1945, July 11 Died near Cashtown, Pa.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Mira Lloyd Dock (1853-1945) span the years 1814-1951, with the bulk of the material dating from 1899 to 1945. The papers are in English and German and are organized into Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Miscellany, and Oversize series primarily relating to Dock's involvement in horticulture, forestry, conservation, and forestry education in Pennsylvania and elsewhere in the United States as well as in Germany and England.
The Correspondence series covers Dock's early efforts, her years as the first woman on the State Forestry Reservation Commission of Pennsylvania, and her work through women's organizations such as the General Federation of Women's Clubs and the State Federation of Pennsylvania Women in the areas of conservation, forestry, horticulture, forestry education, and city beautification. Notable correspondents include F. Bascom, Sir Dietrich Brandis, Marion A. Crocker, T. B. Jäger, Warren H. Manning, J. Horace McFarland, Gifford Pinchot, Joseph T. Rothrock, Charles Sprague Sargent, Mary Belle King Sherman, and H. A. Surface.
Also in the Correspondence are letters from family member William Dean Howells as well as letters concerning Dock and Lloyd family genealogy. Early nineteenth-century correspondence written by Dock and Lloyd ancestors is supplemented in the Miscellany series by an 1864 contract with Gilliard Dock for work on the Lorberry Creek Railroad in Pennsylvania.
The Speeches and Writings span Dock's career and cover topics such as forest conservation; forest fires; playgrounds; park development; forestry education; Arbor Day; city beautification of Harrisburg, Pennsylvania; gardening; John Bartram; and tree species. Included is a draft and printed version of a report documenting her 1899 trip to Europe, most notably to England and the Black Forest of Germany. Other reports include those written for the State Forestry Reservation Commission of Pennsylvania and various women's clubs.
The Miscellany is comprised mostly of newspaper clippings and printed matter relating to Dock's interest in forestry, conservation, horticulture, and genealogy.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in four series:
Correspondence, 1814-1951
Speeches and Writings, 1840-1936
Miscellany, 1836-1944
Oversize, 1890-1921
Container List
- Correspondence, 1814-1951 (Box 1-7)
  Correspondence with colleagues and family.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1814-1872 (Box 1)
  - 1886-1902, (6 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1903-1909, (7 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1910-1914, (6 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1915-1916, (6 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1917-1924, (6 folders) (Box 5)
  - 1925-1934, (7 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1935-1951, undated, (4 folders) (Box 7)
- Speeches and Writings, 1840-1936 (Box 7-8)
  Notes, drafts, and printed copies of speeches, writings, papers, and reports.
  - General (Box 7)
    - 1896-1906, (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - 1907-1929, undated, (6 folders) (Box 8)
  - Notes, 1840-1854, 1903-1917, 1926, 1936, undated (Box 8)
- Miscellany, 1836-1944 (Box 9-11)
  Blueprint, contract for work, maps, newspaper clippings, photographs, postcards, printed matter, and subject files.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material or subject and therein chronologically.
  - Blueprint, undated (Box 9)
  - Contract for work, Lorberry Creek Railroad, Pennsylavania, 1864 (Box 9)
  - Forestry and horticultural schools, circa 1919-circa 1922 (Box 9)
  - General Federation of Women's Clubs, biennial meeting, 1916 For additional material see Container 4, 1916 (Box 9)
  - Maps, 1890, 1906, 1921, 1933, undated See also Oversize (Box 9)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1836, 1874-1879, 1886-1944, undated, (4 folders) (Box 9)
  - Photographs, postcards, and artwork, 1914, undated (Box 9)
  - Printed matter (Box 10)
    - 1843, 1857, 1882-1883, 1892-1913, (6 folders) (Box 10)
    - 1914-1936, undated, (5 folders) (Box 11)
- Oversize, 1890-1921 (Box OV 1)
  Maps.
  Arranged and described according to the series, container, and folder from which the items were removed.
  - Maps, 1890, 1906, 1921, undated, (Container 9) (Box OV 1)